This video is sponsored by boot.dev.
Learn software development through
immersive gamified experiences. Go to
boot.dev and use code wonder to get 25%
off your entire first annual plan.
Currently, every year approximately 60
to 70 million people leave [music] this
earth,
this existence.
We don't know where they go, if
anywhere.
We don't know what happens,
>> [music]
>> if anything.
Every day, that number is approximately
175,000 people.
On a daily basis, entire lineages come
to an end. Chunks of generations [music]
are torn off.
Hundreds of thousands of families are
fragmented, hearts broken, psyches
forever altered. Each individual's
departure taking with them pieces of
this earth
>> [music]
>> and those who remain.
One day, that will be you.
The day will be yours, and it will be
you who departs and leaves behind
[music] a changed world.
It's appallingly cliché to say that we
never know when that day will come,
when it will be [music] ours.
Though it's true, of course. For the
most part, for most of us, [music] we
don't know.
But we can estimate.
We can estimate, for example, what the
odds are of dying tomorrow.
On average, every [music] day, the odds
that a person dies, of any age and any
health, are approximately 1 in 47,000.
That's about a 0.002%
chance.
This figure is a rough approximation
based on global population and average
mortality numbers. It's meaningfully
skewed by individuals both in the very
early and very late stages of life, as
well as those with pre-existing ailments
and health conditions.
If rather, you're around 30 years old
and reasonably healthy, obviously, your
odds of dying tomorrow go considerably
down. [music]
But of course, not to zero.
It's never zero until it's happened.
Variables like your lifestyle, the place
you live, the things and people you
encounter, the risks you take, your sex,
and so on, all also change the odds up
or down for you. Thrill seekers tend to
have a much higher chance of premature
death.
Females, in general, tend to have a much
lower one.
There are many ways to die prematurely
and unexpectedly.
Some are far less pleasant. Some are far
more absurd.
Annually, there's roughly a one in 112
million chance that you die because of a
vending machine. That's clearly very
unlikely, but it's actually almost three
times more likely than winning the
Powerball jackpot. And people win that
[music] every year.
Annually, there's a one in 11 million
chance you die because of an elevator or
escalator. There's about a one in a
million chance you die because of a
tree, about the same chance you die
because of a bathtub, one in a 160,000
chance by a natural disaster, one in
about 50,000 by choking, one in 40,000
by fire, a one in 17,000 chance of a
heat-related death in any given year,
which is also the same chance as being
killed by another human annually.
There's a one in 16,000 chance you die
by accidental overdose, and a one in
7,000 chance by a car accident.
Altogether, assuming you're a
30-year-old healthy male, the odds that
you die tomorrow of an unforeseeable,
non-health or age-related event are
approximately one in 250,000.
That's about a 0.0004%
chance.
If you're a 30-year-old healthy female,
the odds go down to about one in
800,000, about three times less likely.
All this is calculated roughly from data
on age-specific deaths by external
causes, averaged out across the year,
totaled up, and then converted into
daily odds.
For most of us, none of these sorts of
aforementioned events will happen. In
all likelihood, you can go to bed
tonight and be confident that tomorrow
morning your eyes [music] will open and
your day will be full.
Same with the next day, and the next
day, and the next day.
Of course, however, [music]
with each tomorrow, regardless of the
ultimate cause of your death, your odds
inevitably climb.
Old age becomes your age. Possibilities
become probable. [music]
Instead of tomorrow, the odds you die in
the next year of an unforeseeable
external event for an average healthy
30-year-old male are roughly 1 in 700.
The odds within the next decade [music]
are roughly 1 in 70.
Things only get a lot worse from there.
And if we include health and age-related
causes, [music]
the odds that a 30-year-old male dies
within the next decade are 1 in 37
[music]
or nearly a 3% chance.
Still low, but getting eerily [music]
starting.
Of course, by far the most common cause
of death
>> [music]
>> is life.
Being born is the guarantor of it.
If you're alive right now, [music]
the chances you die are ultimately 1 in
1.
When considered in these terms, with
death being contingent on life, [music]
in a broader and deeper sense, the odds
of dying don't go up.
They become infinitesimal.
This is because the odds of being born,
being alive,
>> [music]
>> are so preposterously tiny,
dying becomes a kind of miracle.
For you specifically to exist, to have
been born, of course, [music] your
mother and father had to exist. They had
to exist in a similar area of the world
or [music] happen to visit and be in the
same area at the same time.
They also had to meet.
It's estimated that for two specific
people to meet within a lifetime, it is
a roughly 1 in 20,000 chance.
That's less likely than you being killed
by another human this [music] year.
And that's just meeting.
Your parents had to do a lot more than
that.
>> [music]
>> They had to meet within a specific time
window that allowed for reproduction,
and they had to like each other enough
in [music] some way to reproduce.
What are the odds of attraction?
What are the odds of love?
Incalculable.
All of that is before the dance even
starts.
A female human body has approximately
300,000 eggs. A male can have as many as
several trillions of sperm cells across
their lifetime.
>> [music]
>> The odds that a specific egg and a
specific sperm combine and produce a
specific person
>> [music]
>> are less than one in a quadrillion.
This unfathomable pairing had to happen
for you and both your parents. It had to
happen for both their parents, for their
parents' parents,
>> [music]
>> for their parents' parents' parents, so
on and so forth, all the way back to the
first humans, [music]
to the early species that evolved into
humans,
to the first living creatures on Earth.
Tiny microbes at the bottom of the ocean
that divided, [music] replicated, and
eventually gave rise to complex
eukaryotic life.
Your existence [music] fundamentally
depended on the emergence of these
microbes and a subsequent
billion-year-long chain of propagation.
Your ancestors are not merely distant in
time,
>> [music]
>> but in form.
What are the odds these microbes have
even came to exist in the first place?
You being alive is not only contingent
on the incalculable odds of all the
humans and creatures that needed to
exist and encounter each other at just
the right time and just the right place,
but also the odds of there being a time
and place for which creatures and humans
might exist and evolve at all.
"Not how the world is is the mystical,
but that it is." wrote philosopher
Ludwig Wittgenstein.
As far as we know, the only life in the
cosmos exists here on Earth.
Even if there are many other planets
with life on them, life beginning,
surviving, and evolving depend on very
specific conditions. A planet must find
itself in a habitable zone of the
universe, a location with just the right
proximity [music] to a star where the
planet's surface temperature allows for
liquid water.
It can't be too cold, can't be too hot.
There also seems to be a need for the
presence of elements like hydrogen,
oxygen, and carbon, as well as enough
gravity to sustain [music] an
atmosphere.
Far more absurd than that, any possible
planetary conditions at all depend on
incredibly specific laws and constants
in the universe. [music]
For any planet to form, there must be
certain potential arrangements of matter
and energy, all held together by a force
of gravity [music] with just the right
tension. The dimensions of space-time
must allow for such gravitational force
in the orbiting of gas and dust to
coalesce. The very existence of matter
and energy must be present, prevalent,
and stable enough to spread out and form
into stellar objects.
If anything were different, even by a
slight degree, like the strength of
gravity or the dimensions of space-time
or the nature of energy, it isn't clear
what would materialize.
It isn't clear if stars and planets and
galaxies would ever form. [music]
It isn't clear if there would be carbon.
It isn't clear if there would ever be
the possibility of life.
We on Earth have just awakened to the
great oceans of space and time from
which we have emerged. We are the legacy
of 15 billion years of cosmic evolution,
said Carl Sagan.
Despite apparently being one of the most
inconceivably unlikely things in the
universe, [music]
the odds of you currently existing are,
of course, 100%.
Because here you are.
Even if you happen to pull the lottery
ticket of death tomorrow, to have been
here even for a moment, [music] let
alone enough moments to know of moments,
to know of odds, to know of
possibilities,
to know of all that you can and do,
[music]
is so strange and absurd, it's
impossible to grasp.
It is so unbelievably unlikely [music]
to die,
and yet you get to.
We all get to.
If there is anything [music] worth
worshipping,
perhaps
it is the odds.
>> [music]
>> While the odds remain in our favor, we
obviously want to use our time wisely,
pursuing our interests, engaging with
the world in meaningful ways, and
enjoying ourselves along the way. One
powerful way to do this is through the
skill of coding.
This video's sponsor, [music]
boot.dev, makes learning and leveling up
your programming skills literally a
game. Immersive, fun, and effective.
Not only is programming a fascinating
discipline with near endless
possibilities for expression,
>> [music]
>> but it's also an extremely valuable
skill. The median salary for back-end
developers in the United States [music]
is well over $100,000.
What stands out to me about boot.dev,
that's super unique and effective, is
that instead of lectures or passive
information, it's essentially a
programming RPG
>> [music]
>> that uses modern game design to immerse
you into coding. Learn Python, SQL, and
Go. Build book bots, static sites,
[music]
and so much more. All while going on
quests, fighting bosses, and earning XP
and levels.
>> [music]
>> Every challenge and achievement is
something you can directly apply to the
real world, whether it's passing
technical interviews, building a
successful programming career, [music]
or creating your own web applications
and services. And if you're ever stuck,
Boots, a bear wizard, is always around
[music] to help you.
All content is free to read and watch,
and a paid membership unlocks the
interactive features and game [music]
mechanics with a 30-day, no questions
asked, refund policy.
Go to boot.dev and use code wonder
[music]
to get 25% off your entire first annual
plan and begin your own journey today.
And of course, [music] as always, thank
you so much for watching in general.
And see you next video.